whsmith.co.uk 2019-02-03

# Privacy policy & cookies | WHSmith

## Frequently Asked Questions

  * Privacy Policy
  * Cookie policy

## WHSMITH PRIVACY POLICY

WHSmith.co.uk wants you to be able to shop with confidence on our site, which is **why we take the privacy of your personal information very seriously**. We respect your privacy and are committed to protecting your personal data. This privacy notice will inform you as to how we look after your personal data when you visit our website (regardless of where you visit it from) and tell you about your privacy rights and how the law protects you. By using our website or any of our services, or providing us with any personal data, you agree to your personal data being used and disclosed in the manner set out in this policy. 

Back to top

## PURPOSE OF THIS PRIVACY NOTICE

This privacy notice aims to give you information on how WHSmith collects and processes your personal data through your use of this website, including any data you may provide through this website when you shop with us.

WH Smith High Street Limited is the data controller and is responsible for your personal data (collectively referred to as "WHSmith", "we", "us" or "our" in this privacy notice).

It is important that the personal data we hold about you is accurate and current. Please keep us informed if your personal data changes during your relationship with us. 

## HOW WE USE YOUR PERSONAL DATA

We will only use your personal data when the law allows us to, and only for the purposes agreed to when you provided it. Most commonly, we will use your personal data in the following circumstances:

  * Where we need to perform the contract we are about to enter into or have entered into with you.
  * Where it is necessary for our legitimate interests (or those of a third party) and your interests and fundamental rights do not override those interests.
  * Where we need to comply with a legal or regulatory obligation.

Generally we do not rely on consent as a legal basis for processing your personal data other than in relation to sending third party direct marketing communications to you via email or text message. You have the right to withdraw consent to marketing at any time by contacting us at [support@whsmith.co.uk](mailto:support@whsmith.co.uk) or by 'opting out' of marketing communications in any e-mail sent to you. 

## PURPOSES FOR WHICH WE WILL USE YOUR PERSONAL DATA

We will use your personal data to:

  * Register you as a new customer
  * Process and deliver your order(s) including:
  * \- Managing payments, fees and charges
  * \- Collecting and recovering money owed to us
  * To manage our relationship with you which will include:
  * \- Notifying you about changes to our terms or privacy policy
  * \- Asking you to leave a review or take a survey**
  * To enable you to partake in a prize draw, competition or complete a survey**
  * To administer and protect our business and this website (including troubleshooting, data analysis, testing, system maintenance, support, reporting and hosting of data)
  * To deliver relevant website content and advertisements to you and measure or understand the effectiveness of the advertising we serve to you**
  * To use data analytics to improve our website, products/services, marketing, customer relationships and experiences
  * To make suggestions and recommendations to you about goods or services that may be of interest to you**

## HOW IS YOUR PERSONAL DATA COLLECTED? 

We use different methods to collect data from and about you including through:

  * **Direct interactions.** You may give us your personal information by filling in forms or by corresponding with us by post, phone, e-mail or otherwise. This includes information you provide when you:
  * \- purchase any of our products or services;
  * \- create an account on our website;
  * \- subscribe to our newsletters or other publications;
  * \- enter a competition, promotion or survey; or
  * \- give us some feedback.
  * **Automated technologies or interactions.** As you interact with our website, we may automatically collect Technical Data about your equipment, browsing actions and patterns. We collect this personal data by using cookies and other similar technologies. 
  * **Third parties or publicly available sources.** We may collect technical information about your journey through our site with Google Analytics. We and our authorised partners use this data to improve your site experience.

## YOUR LEGAL RIGHTS

You have the right to: 

  * **Request what personal data** we hold about you;
  * **Request any corrections** to the personal data that we hold about you;
  * **Request erasure** of your personal data;
  * **Object to processing** of your personal data where we are relying on a legitimate interest (or those of a third party) and there is something about your particular situation which makes you want to object to processing on this ground;
  * **Request restriction of processing** of your personal data;
  * **Request the transfer** of your personal data to you or to a third party; or
  * **Withdraw consent at any time** where we are relying on consent to process your personal data.

You will not have to pay a fee to access your personal data (or to exercise any of the other rights). However, we may charge a reasonable fee if your request is clearly unfounded, repetitive or excessive. Alternatively, we may refuse to comply with your request in these circumstances.

We may need to request specific information from you to help us confirm your identity and ensure your right to access your personal data (or to exercise any of your other rights). This is a security measure to ensure that personal data is not disclosed to any person who has no right to receive it. We may also contact you to ask you for further information in relation to your request to speed up our response.

We may need to request specific information from you to help us confirm your identity and ensure your right to access your personal data (or to exercise any of your other rights). This is a security measure to ensure that personal data is not disclosed to any person who has no right to receive it. We may also contact you to ask you for further information in relation to your request to speed up our response.

## THE DATA WE COLLECT ABOUT YOU 

Personal data, or personal information, means any information about an individual from which that person can be identified. It does not include data where the identity has been removed (anonymous data).

When you complete an online form, register or shop with us online, we may collect, use and store different kinds of personal data about you such as your name, gender, date of birth, billing/delivery address, e-mail address and telephone number. We may also collect and retain information about your interactions with us either in store, online or through our contact centres so that we can process your transactions and deal with any future queries.

We also collect, use and share Aggregated Data such as statistical or demographic data for any purpose. **Aggregated Data** may be derived from your personal data but is not considered personal data in law as this data does not directly or indirectly reveal your identity. For example, we may aggregate your Usage Data to calculate the percentage of users accessing a specific website feature. However, if we combine or connect Aggregated Data with your personal data so that it can directly or indirectly identify you, we treat the combined data as personal data which will be used in accordance with this privacy notice.

We do not collect any **Special Categories of Personal Data** about you (this includes details about your race or ethnicity, religious or philosophical beliefs, sex life, sexual orientation, political opinions, trade union membership, information about your health and genetic and biometric data). Nor do we collect any information about criminal convictions and offences.

## CONSENT

In certain situations, we can collect and process your data with your consent. 

In limited situations, we may approach you for your written consent to allow us to process certain particularly sensitive data. If we do so, we will provide you with full details of the information that we would like and the reason we need it, so that you can carefully consider whether you wish to consent. You should be aware that it is not a condition of your contract with us that you agree to any request for consent from us.

When collecting your personal data, we'll always make clear to you which data is necessary in connection with a particular contractual or legal requirement. 

We may process your personal data without your knowledge or consent (for example, in relation to fraud management or to assist with investigations by the police or other regulatory bodies) in compliance with the above rules, where this is required or permitted by law.

## OPTING OUT

You can ask us or third parties to stop sending you marketing messages at any time by contacting us at [support@whsmith.co.uk](mailto:support@whsmith.co.uk) or by 'opting out' of marketing communications in any e-mail sent to you.

In some circumstances you can ask us to delete your data by making a 'Request for Erasure'. In order to make such a request, please write to us at [support@whsmith.co.uk](mailto:support@whsmith.co.uk). Following your request, your personal data shall be removed from our database without undue delay in accordance with statutory requirements. Our DPO shall thereafter take reasonable steps to inform any third parties who may be processing any personal data they hold about you that you have requested the erasure of any links to, or copy or replication of, your personal data. 

## COOKIES

You can set your browser to refuse all or some browser cookies, or to alert you when websites set or access cookies. If you disable or refuse cookies, please note that some parts of this website may become inaccessible or not function properly. For more information about the cookies we use, please see our Cookie policy.

## PROMOTIONAL OFFERS FROM US

We may use your Identity, Contact, Technical, Usage and Profile Data to form a view on what we think you may want or need, or what may be of interest to you. This is how we decide which products, services and offers may be relevant for you.**

## MARKETING 

We strive to provide you with choices regarding certain personal data uses, particularly around marketing and advertising. Should you wish to unsubscribe to any or all of our marketing material, please contact at [support@whsmith.co.uk](mailto:support@whsmith.co.uk) or opt out of marketing communications by clicking the 'unsubscribe' link in any e-mail sent to you. 

## OFF SITE MARKETING

Whilst browsing other websites you may see WHSmith promotional messages, these will be displayed based on cookies placed during your recent visit to our website. Personal information is not used in the delivery of these promotional messages. Please see our Cookie policy for more detail. 

## THIRD-PARTY MARKETING 

We will get your express opt-in consent before we share your personal data with any company outside the WHSmith group of companies for marketing purposes.

## THIRD-PARTY LINKS 

Clicking on links to third-party websites, plug-ins and applications contained within this website, or enabling those connections, may allow third parties to collect or share data about you. We do not control these third-party websites and are not responsible for their privacy statements. When you leave our website, we encourage you to read the privacy notice of every website you visit.

## DISCLOSURES OF YOUR PERSONAL DATA: 

We may have to share your personal data with the parties set out below for the purposes set out above (in 'Purposes for which we will use your Personal Data'):

  * Other WHSmith group entities, details of which can be found in our [ Annual Reports;](http://www.whsmithplc.co.uk/investors/company_reports/annual_reports)
  * Third party suppliers in order to fulfil orders placed by you; or
  * We may, from time to time, expand, reduce or sell WHSmith and this may involve the transfer of divisions or the whole business to new owners. If this happens, your personal data will, where relevant, be transferred to the new owner or controlling party, under the terms of this Privacy Notice.

We require all third parties to respect the security of your personal data and to treat it in accordance with the law. We do not allow our third-party service providers to use your personal data for their own purposes and only permit them to process your personal data for specified purposes and in accordance with our instructions.

## INTERNATIONAL TRANSFERS 

We do not transfer your personal data outside the European Economic Area ( **EEA** ).

## DATA SECURITY 

We have appropriate security measures in place to prevent your personal data from being accidentally lost, used or accessed in an unauthorised way, altered or disclosed. In addition, we limit access to your personal data to those employees, agents, contractors and other third parties who have a business need to know. They will only process your personal data on our instructions and they are subject to a duty of confidentiality.

We have procedures in place to deal with any suspected personal data breach and will notify you and any applicable regulator of a breach where we are legally required to do so.

## HOW LONG WILL YOU USE MY PERSONAL DATA FOR? 

We will only retain your personal data for as long as necessary to fulfil the purposes we collected it for, including for the purposes of satisfying any legal, accounting, or reporting requirements.

To determine the appropriate retention period for personal data, we consider the amount, nature, and sensitivity of the personal data, the potential risk of harm from unauthorised use or disclosure of your personal data, the purposes for which we process your personal data and whether we can achieve those purposes through other means, and the applicable legal requirements.

In some circumstances we may anonymise your personal data (so that it can no longer be associated with you) for research or statistical purposes in which case we may use this information indefinitely without further notice to you.

## IF YOU FAIL TO PROVIDE YOUR PERSONAL DATA 

Where we need to collect personal data by law, or under the terms of a contract we have with you and you fail to provide that data when requested, we may not be able to perform the contract we have or are trying to enter into with you (for example, to provide you with goods or services). In this case, we may have to cancel a product or service you have with us but we will notify you if this is the case at the time.

## DATA PROTECTION OFFICER 

We have appointed a Data Protection Officer ("DPO") who is responsible for overseeing questions in relation to this privacy notice. If you have any questions about this privacy notice, including any requests to exercise your legal rights, please contact Data Protection Officer, WHSmith, Greenbridge Road, Swindon SN3 3LD or e-mail [support@whsmith.co.uk](mailto:support@whsmith.co.uk). 

## CONTACTING THE REGULATOR

If you feel that your data has not been handled correctly, or you wish to make a complaint, you have the right to contact the Information Commissioner's Office ("ICO"), the UK supervisory authority for data protection issues, at any time. You can contact them by telephone (0303 123 1113) or via their website (<http://www.ico.org.uk/concerns>). We would, however, be grateful for the chance to deal with your concerns before you approach the ICO so please contact us in the first instance.

## GENERAL

It is likely that we will need to update this Privacy Policy from time to time. We will notify you of any significant changes via our newsletters.

** These activities require your explicit consent (please see the 'CONSENT' section above).

Back to top

## Cookie policy

Cookies are small text files. Many websites place cookies on your computer when you visit. Cookies are used to make websites work, or to make them work more efficiently, and to provide useful information to website operators.

Many web browsers allow users to control most cookies through their browser settings. However doing so will prevent the checkout from working and you will not be able to place orders.

**The table here explains what cookies we use and why**. More information about cookies, including details on viewing what cookies have been set and how to delete them is available at [allaboutcookies.org.](http://www.allaboutcookies.org/)

## The Cookies we use and what they do

**Name** | **Technical Name** | **Purpose** | **Retention Period**  
---|---|---|---  
User and Session ID | JSESSIONID | Unique user session identifier to handle things such as the products and offers you have put in your basket basket | Expires at end of session  
Checkout 1 | 

K-JSESSIONID-gdn caooa

| When you move from one checkout step to another, this cookie let the system know that youâ€™re the same customer at each step | Expires at end of session  
Checkout 2 | X-Mapping-gbooldlg | When you move from one checkout step to another, this cookie let the system know that youâ€™re the same customer at each step | Expires at end of session  
Country default | country_iso | Sets the country settings displayed on the website.Â  For us this is fixed as UK. | 60 days  
Currency default | currency_iso | Sets the currency displayed on the website.Â  For us this is fixed as pounds sterling. | 60 days  
Language default | language_iso | Sets the language displayed on the website.Â  For us this is fixed as English. | 31 days  
Product List View | 

view_format

| The number of columns of products shown on the listings page | Expires at end of session  
Last Category Page | 

lastSuccessfulCategory

| Used to store the most recently viewed category page. Helpful when generating breadcrumbs that are more accurate to the users journey. | 31 days  
Last Category | fcp_last_category | last browsed category, used for breadcrumbs | 31 days  
Shopping basket | 

fcp_shopping_basket

| Retains the customer's shopping basket contents between sessions. | Set by WHS  
Google Analytics User | __utma | Google Analytics (GA) tracking cookies are used to provide reports about our site visitors. These cookies do not collect any personal data about you. For Google Analytics: Each unique browser that visits a page on the site is provided with a unique ID therefore subsequent visits to the website via the same browser are recorded as belonging to the same (unique) visitor.  | 730 days (2 years)  
Google Analytics Session | __utmb, __utmc  | For Google Analytics: These cookies establish that an anonymous user has started a session. | Expires at end of session  
Google Analytics Origin | __utmz | For Google Analytics: When visitors reach the site via a search engine result, a direct link, or an ad that links to the page, Google Analytics stores the type of referral information in a cookie.  | 182 days (6 months)  
Google Analytics Custom | __utmv | For Google Analytics: This cookie enables us to identify specific actions by a user. This is not currently used.  | 730 days (2 years)  
N/A | IDE | These cookies are used to remember user preferences and display relevant advertising to users around the web | 2 years  
N/A | id | These cookies are used to remember user preferences and display relevant advertising to users around the web | 2 years  
N/A | DSID | These cookies are used to remember user preferences and display relevant advertising to users around the web | 1 hour  
N/A | GED_PLAYLIST_ACTIVITY | These cookies are used to remember user preferences and display relevant advertising to users around the web | Deleted on close of browser window  
SLIBeacon | SLIBeacon | Unique id for the user | 2 years  
SLI1_xxxxxxx | SLI1_xxxxxxx | Purpose | 30 minutes  
SLI2_xxxxxxx | SLI2_xxxxxxx | The user id and page and search load counts | End of session  
SLI4_xxxxxxx | SLI4_xxxxxxx | Timestamp of last search | 6 months  
uid | uid | Tracking search activity for learning | 1 year  
_mvt | _mvt | Stores the user designation | 2 years  
sli-rr | sli-rr | Array of refinement topic/value pairs along with a timestamp representing when the refinement value was selected  | 1 year  
sli-rv | sli-rv | Array of skus/timestamp pairs, where the sku represents the product that was viewed and the timestamp represents when the product was viewed  | 1 year  
Google Universal Analytics | _ga | This cookie is used to distinguish unique users by assigning a randomly generated number as a client identifier. | 2 years  
Google Universal Analytics | _gat | Used to throttle the request rate - limiting the collection of data on high traffic sites | 10 minutes  
Devatics Session  | _dec | Unique user session identifier to handle things such as the identification of the interactions done on the site.  | Retention  
Devatics User  | _dez | Unique user identifier used to anonymously identify a visitor across the different visits of the site.  | Expires within 365 days   
Devatics Data  | _ded  | Used to store information during the visit: page viewed, Devatics message displayed, products added to the cart | Expires at the end of the session   
sli_uuid | sli_uuid | A unique id for the user Persistent | 10 years  
DoubleClick | doubleclick.net | DoubleClick uses cookies to improve advertising. Some common applications are to target advertising based on what’s relevant to a user, to improve reporting on campaign performance, and to avoid showing ads the user has already seen. | 18 months  
ContentSquare | _cs_id | This cookie contains ContentSquare’s user identifier | 13 months  
ContentSquare | _cs_s | This cookie contains the number of pageviews within the running session for ContentSquare Solution | 30 minutes  
ContentSquare | _cs_vars | This cookie is used by ContentSquare to record custom variables | Expires at the end of the session   
ContentSquare | _cs_ex | This cookies is used by ContentSquare to exclude some visitors from the collection | 30 days  
ContentSquare | _cs_c | This cookies is used by ContentSquare to save the user consent to be tracked | 13 months  
ContentSquare | _cs_optout | This cookies is used by ContentSquare to exclude some visitors from the collection | 3 years  
  
Back to top
